ベテル奉仕や建設奉仕を
行える兄弟姉妹が
There is an ongoing need
for volunteers at Bethel
and on theocratic construction projects.
さらに必要とされています
新型コロナウイルス感染症のために
Although the COVID-19 pandemic has limited
現在招待できる人数は限られていますが
the number of those who may be invited
at this time,
奉仕者が必要であることに
変わりはありません
there is still a need for volunteers.
As you watch the following video,
次のビデオを見ながら
please note the spirit displayed
ベテル奉仕を行っている兄弟姉妹が
by those who make themselves available
for Bethel service.
どんな精神を示しているかに
注目しましょう
Making yourself available for Bethel service
ベテル奉仕をするなら
エホバに一層仕える機会が開かれます
is like knocking on a door that leads
to many other privileges of service.
Of course, to serve at Bethel
もちろん ベテル奉仕には
requires a self-sacrificing spirit
どんな仕事でも喜んで行う
自己犠牲の精神が必要です
and a willingness to serve
wherever there is a need,
預言者イザヤの精神です
in harmony with the attitude
displayed by the prophet Isaiah
イザヤ 6:8にはこうあります
at Isaiah 6:8:
「私はエホバの声を聞いた
“Then I heard the voice of Jehovah saying:
『私は誰を遣わそうか
誰が私たちのために行くだろうか』
“‘Whom shall I send, and who will go for us?’
⋯⋯私は言った
And I said: ‘Here I am! Send me!’”
『ここに私がおります！
私を遣わしてください！』」
When Isaiah learned about an opportunity
イザヤはエホバのために
もっと働くことができると知ったとき
to do more in Jehovah’s service,
he responded eagerly,
目を輝かせました
even though he did not know exactly
what he was going to be assigned to do.
どんな仕事が割り当てられるかは
知りませんでしたが
エホバが特別な奉仕を行うよう
It was enough for him to know
that Jehovah was extending an invitation
勧めてくださった ということ
だけで十分でした
to serve in a special way,
ぜひ行いたいと思いました
and Isaiah wanted to volunteer.
この同じ精神を世界中の
ベテル家族の成員も示しています
The same spirit is shown
by Bethel family members worldwide.
If the Branch Committee determines
that there is a need for your services,
あなたがベテル奉仕を行うか
神権的な建設プロジェクトに加わるかは
they will decide where you can best be used,
支部委員会が決定します
whether at Bethel or perhaps
on a theocratic construction assignment.
Submitting your application
may open a door of opportunity
申込書を提出すれば
エホバと組織のために奉仕する
to serve Jehovah and his organization
in a variety of ways.
さまざまな機会が
開かれるかもしれません
今ご覧いただいたのは
That was an excerpt from the video
「ベテル奉仕ができますか」
というビデオの一部です
Making Yourself Available for Bethel Service.
If you are interested in serving at Bethel
ベテル奉仕や建設奉仕に関心があり
or on theocratic construction projects
申し込みたいと思っていますか
on a part-time or full-time basis,
フルタイムかパートタイムを選べます
please watch the entire video on jw.org.
ぜひビデオ全体を
jw.orgでご覧ください
バプテスマを受けたクリスチャンで
19歳以上の方は
Baptized Christians who are
19 years of age or older
ぜひ検討して積極的に
申し込んでください
and are interested in volunteering
should apply.
Speak to your congregation secretary
for more information.
会衆の書記から さらに情報を
得ることができます
もし可能でしたら jw.orgで
If possible, please submit
your application electronically
電子的に申込書を提出してください
on jw.org.
あなたは平和が脅かされる状況に
直面したことがありますか
Have you ever found yourself in a situation
where your peace was threatened?
How did you handle it?
どうしましたか
We can learn much
from the faithful man Jacob
忠実なヤコブの手本から
平和をつくることについて
多くのことを学べます
about how to make peace.
Please open your Bibles
to Genesis chapter 26,
どうぞ創世記26章をお開きください
聖書を目で追いながら 劇形式の
聖書朗読をお聞きください
and follow along as Brother Mark Sanderson,
a member of the Governing Body,
applies the lessons
統治体のマーク・サンダーソン兄弟が
in the dramatic Bible reading
with the theme
学べる点について話してくださいます
“{
主題は 「ヤコブ 平和を愛した人」
Have you ever been
the victim of oppression or injustice?
誰かからひどいことをされたことが
これまでありましたか
Have you been angered by something
嫌なことを言われて
カチンときたことがありますか
someone has said or done?
みんなあるはずです
Who of us hasn’t?
そういうとき 世の中の多くの人は
In situations like that,
people who don’t know Jehovah
平和を大事にして穏やかに
対応しようとしたりはしません
often react in a way
that’s far from peaceful.
仕返しをします やられたらやり返す
They retaliate; they fight;
それが普通です
they hit back.
でも 私たちは違います
But we know that Jehovah
sees what happened,
エホバが見ていて 必要なら
正してくれることを知っています
and he can set matters straight.
We’re wise to remember the words of Jesus:
イエス･キリストはこう教えました
「温和な人たちは幸福です」
“Happy are the mild-tempered.”
「平和をつくる人たちは幸福です」
“Happy are the peacemakers.”
The Bible describes a man
who remained mild and peaceable
聖書には 非常に理不尽な目に遭っても
温和に対応し 平和をつくった
ある人のことが書かれています
in some extremely difficult
and stressful situations.
何度嫌な目に遭っても
決して争いませんでした
Repeatedly, he chose not to fight,
平和のためにできることを
一生懸命にしました
preferring a course that led to peace.
その人とは ヤコブです
That man was Jacob.
ヤコブは父親のイサクから
Jacob learned from the peaceful example
平和の大切さについて学びました
of his father, Isaac.
There was a famine in the land,
ある時 飢饉が起き
イサクは家族でゲラルに移り住みました
and Isaac moved his family to Gerar,
そこはフィリスティア人の
王アビメレクが治めていました
which was ruled by Abimelech,
king of the Philistines.
そこでどんな問題が起き
Let’s read about the problems that arose
イサクはどのように対応したでしょうか
and see how Isaac dealt with them.
どうぞ 創世記26章12節を
開いてください
Please turn to Genesis 26:12.
“And Isaac began to sow seed in that land,
イサクはその土地で種をまいた
その年の収穫は
まいた物の百倍にもなった
“and in that year he reaped
100 times what he sowed,
エホバが祝福したからだった
“for Jehovah was blessing him.
イサクは裕福になり
その後も成功していき
“The man became wealthy,
“and he continued to prosper
until he became very wealthy.
非常に裕福になった
幾つもの羊の群れと牛の群れを持ち
“He acquired flocks of sheep
and herds of cattle
大勢の召し使いを
抱えるようになったのである
“and a large body of servants,
それでフィリスティア人は
彼をねたむようになった
“and the Philistines began to envy him.
“So the Philistines took soil
フィリスティア人は
父アブラハムの時代に
“and stopped up all the wells
that his father’s servants had dug
召し使いたちが掘った井戸
全てに土を詰め ふさいだ
“in the days of Abraham.
アビメレクはイサクに言った
“Abimelech then said to Isaac:
あなたは私たちより
はるかに強くなりました
“‘Move from our neighborhood,
for you have grown far stronger than we are.’
私たちの所から出ていってください
“So Isaac moved from there
and encamped in the valley of Gerar
それでイサクはそこから移動し
“and began dwelling there.
ゲラルの谷に宿営を張って住んだ
“And Isaac again dug the wells
イサクは 父アブラハムの時代に掘られ
“that had been dug
in the days of his father Abraham
アブラハムの死後フィリスティア人に
ふさがれた井戸を掘り直した
“but that the Philistines had stopped up
after Abraham’s death,
そして それぞれの井戸を
父が付けた名前で呼んだ
“and he called them by the names
that his father had given them.
“When the servants of Isaac
were digging in the valley,
イサクの召し使いたちが
谷で井戸を掘ると
“they found a well of fresh water.
きれいな水が出てきた
するとゲラルの羊飼いたちが
“And the shepherds of Gerar
“began quarreling
with the shepherds of Isaac, saying:
その水はわれわれのものだ と言って
イサクの羊飼いたちと言い争いを始めた
“‘The water is ours!’
“So he named the well Esek,
その井戸はエセクと名付けられた
“because they had quarreled with him.
言い争いがあったからだった
“And they started digging another well,
別の井戸を掘ると それを巡って
またも言い争いが起きた
“and they began quarreling over it also.
その井戸はシトナと名付けられた
“So he named it Sitnah.
その後イサクはそこから移動して
別の井戸を掘った
“Later he moved away from there
and dug another well,
今度は言い争いが起きなかった
“but they did not quarrel over it.
その井戸はレホボトと名付けられた
“So he named it Rehoboth and said:
イサクが言うには
エホバが広い場所を与え
“‘It is because now Jehovah
has given us ample room
ここで子孫を増やせるように
してくださったからだった
“and has made us fruitful in the land.’
“Then he went up from there to Beersheba.
やがてイサクはそこから
ベエル･シェバに行った
その夜 エホバがイサクに
現れて こう言った
“That night Jehovah appeared to him and said:
私はあなたの父アブラハムの神である
“‘I am the God of your father Abraham.
“‘Do not be afraid, for I am with you,
恐れてはいけない
私はあなたと共にいるからだ
“‘and I will bless you
and multiply your offspring
私に仕えたアブラハムのゆえに
あなたを祝福し
あなたの子孫を多くする
on account of Abraham my servant.’”
The Philistines, motivated by envy,
フィリスティア人たちは
ねたみに駆られて
以前にアブラハムが掘った
井戸を全部ふさぎました
stop up all the wells that Abraham had dug,
そして王は ここから
出ていくようにと言います
and the king asks Isaac
to move from the neighborhood.
イサクはどうするでしょうか
Isaac now has a decision to make.
出ていく必要なんてない
と言う人もいたでしょう
Perhaps some encourage him to stay put.
Think about how they might have reasoned:
誰かがこう言ったかもしれません
「イサク あなたは何も
悪いことをしていません
‘You’ve done nothing wrong, Isaac.
エホバはあなたとあなたの子孫に
‘Jehovah told you that you and your offspring
この地方を与えると
言ったではありませんか
‘would possess the land.
恐れることはありません
‘You have nothing to fear.
あなたにはフィリスティア人よりも
強い召し使いたちがたくさんいます
‘You have many servants,
‘and they’re stronger than the Philistines.
やられたらやり返しましょう
‘Why not hit back
井戸を取り返すために
戦おうではありませんか」
against those who have done this
to your wells?’
In this situation, what would you have done?
こういうとき あなたならどうしますか
イサクは争わずに平和を大切にしました
Isaac chooses a peaceful course.
He decides to move on.
気持ちを切り替えることにしました
そうするのは簡単なことではありません
This is not easy.
イサクにはたくさんの
召し使いたちがいて
Isaac has many servants
and flocks of sheep and herds of cattle.
多くの羊や牛もいました
これまで ここで広い畑を作り
He has tilled the ground and planted seed,
たくさんの収穫がありました
and it’s produced plentifully,
それでも 気持ちを切り替えて
but he leaves that behind and moves on.
そこから出ていくことにしました
ところが トラブルは続きます
But Isaac’s troubles are not over.
行った先の新しい場所で
召し使いたちに井戸を掘らせ
In his new location, his servants dig wells
きれいな水を見つけますが
and find fresh water.
地元の羊飼いたちから
But the shepherds in that area say:
「その水はわれわれのものだ」
と言われます
“The water is ours!”
イサクは別の井戸を掘りますが
Isaac then digs another well,
羊飼いたちはまたも
「われわれのものだ」と言ってきます
but the local shepherds
quarrel about that one too.
でもこの時も
イサクは決して争うことなく
Again, instead of fighting over the matter,
別の場所に移動することにしました
Isaac moves and finally finds a place
そして そこで安心して
暮らせるようになりました
where he can reside in peace.
ヤコブは父親イサクの手本を見て
Jacob saw that his father’s peaceful actions
平和を大切にすれば良い結果になること
had a good effect,
and he knew that Isaac
had received Jehovah’s blessing.
そして エホバに喜んでもらえる
ということを知りました
何を学べるでしょうか
What’s the lesson?
親の皆さん 皆さんの良い手本は
Parents, never underestimate
the powerful effect
子供たちにとって
かけがえのないものです
your good example can have on your children.
そのことを決して忘れないでください
ヤコブには双子の兄エサウがいました
Jacob has a twin brother, Esau.
Of the two, Esau is born first,
兄のエサウと弟のヤコブ
この2人についてエホバは
意外なことを預言しました
but Jehovah foretells
that—contrary to custom—
年上のエサウが年下のヤコブに
仕えるようになると言ったのです
the older Esau will serve
his younger brother.
エホバは2人がそれぞれ
どんな人になるかを知っていました
Jehovah foresees
what kind of personalities they’ll develop,
エサウは残念なことに
and he knows that Esau
will have little appreciation
神から頂けるものを
大切にしない人になります
for spiritual matters.
This becomes evident
エホバが見抜いていたことは
その通りになりました
when Esau exchanges his right as firstborn
エサウはたった1杯の
煮込み料理と引き換えに
for a mere bowl of stew,
長男の権利を売り渡すと言い
sealing the matter with an oath.
ヤコブにそのことを誓いました
長男の権利を売り渡すのは
重大なことでした
But something more is involved.
In selling the birthright,
he also gives up the right
神から特別な祝福を受ける権利を
to receive a prophetic blessing
from his father.
父親から受け継げなく
なってしまうからです
Years pass, Isaac has grown old,
時がたち 年老いたイサクは
長男のために神からの特別な祝福を
願い求める時が来たと感じます
and he decides it’s time to impart
the blessing to his firstborn.
エサウが長男の権利を
売り渡していたことは
He may not know
that Esau had sold his right as firstborn.
知らなかったかもしれません
いずれにしても イサクはエサウに
In any case, he tells Esau
that he will bless him
あなたのために祝福を願い求めるから
but asks him first
まずは野原に行って 獲物を捕ってきて
to provide him with a tasty dish
おいしい料理を作ってほしい
と言います
of fresh game from the field.
母親のリベカが
このやりとりを聞いていました
Rebekah, the twins’ mother,
overhears this conversation
それでヤコブに エサウが
狩りに行っている間に
and persuades Jacob
to impersonate his twin brother
エサウのふりをしてイサクの所に
行くように と言います
while Esau is out hunting.
The plan is successful.
うまくいきました イサクは知らずに
ヤコブのために祝福を願い求めたのです
Isaac unwittingly blesses Jacob!
Esau, at learning of this, is furious.
そのことを知ったエサウは激怒します
どうなるでしょうか
Let’s take up the account
創世記27章41節を
開いて 見てみましょう
from Genesis 27:41.
“However, Esau harbored
animosity against Jacob
父がヤコブのために
祝福を願い求めたので
エサウはヤコブに恨みを抱き
“because of the blessing
his father had given him,
心の中でこう言い続けた
“and Esau kept saying in his heart:
父の死は近い
“‘The days of mourning for my father
are getting closer.
喪の期間が終わったら
弟ヤコブを殺してやる
“After that I am going to kill
Jacob my brother.’
エサウのこの考えを知ったリベカは
すぐに人を遣わして
ヤコブを呼び こう言った
“When the words of her older son Esau
were told to Rebekah,
兄さんのエサウがあなたを殺して
復讐しようとたくらんでいます
“she at once sent for her younger son Jacob
“and said to him: ‘Look!
今すぐ 私の言う通りにしなさい
“‘Your brother Esau is planning
to take revenge by killing you.
ハランにいる私の兄
ラバンの所に逃げなさい
そして あなたの兄さんの
怒りが収まるまで
“‘Now, my son, do as I say.
“‘Get up and run away
to my brother Laban at Haran.
しばらくそこにとどまるのです
あなたに対する兄さんの怒りが静まって
“‘Dwell with him for a while
あなたのしたことを忘れたら
“‘until your brother’s rage calms down,
私は人を遣わしてあなたを呼び戻します
“‘until your brother’s anger
toward you subsides
あなたたち2人を同じ日に
失いたくはありません
“‘and he forgets what you have done to him.
“‘Then I will send for you from there.
その後 リベカは
イサクにこう言い続けた
“Why should I lose both of you in one day?’
ヘト人の娘たちのせいで
生きているのがつらくて仕方ありません
“After that Rebekah kept saying to Isaac:
もしヤコブもこの辺りの娘たちのような
ヘト人の娘を妻にしたら
“‘I am disgusted with my life
because of the daughters of Heth.
私はもう生きていけません
“‘If Jacob ever takes a wife
from the daughters of Heth,
それでイサクはヤコブを呼び
“‘like these daughters of the land,
ヤコブのために祝福を願い こう命じた
“what good is my life?’
“So Isaac called Jacob
カナン地方の娘たちの中から
妻を選んではいけない
“and blessed him and commanded him, saying:
パダン･アラムへ あなたのおじいさん
ベトエルの家族の所へ行き
“‘You must not take a wife
from the daughters of Canaan.
“‘Go away to Paddanaram
そこで妻を選びなさい
“‘to the house of Bethuel,
your mother’s father,
あなたの伯父さんラバンの
娘たちの中から選ぶのだ
“‘and from there take for yourself a wife
“‘from the daughters of Laban,
your mother’s brother.
全能の神があなたを祝福し
多くの子孫を与えてくださる
“‘God Almighty will bless you
and make you fruitful and multiply you,
あなたから必ず 幾つもの民が生まれる
“‘and you will certainly become
a congregation of peoples.
神は アブラハムに約束した祝福を
あなたとあなたの子孫に与えてくださる
“‘And he will give to you
the blessing of Abraham,
“‘to you and to your offspring with you,
あなたがこれまで
外国人として住んできた土地
“‘so that you may take possession of the land
where you have been living as a foreigner,
神がアブラハムに授けた土地は
あなたのものになる
“which God has given to Abraham.’
こうしてイサクはヤコブを送り出し
“So Isaac sent Jacob away,
ヤコブはパダン･アラムへ
ラバンの所へ向けて出発した
“and he departed for Paddanaram,
“to Laban the son of Bethuel the Aramaean,
ラバンはアラム人ベトエルの子で
the brother of Rebekah,
the mother of Jacob and Esau.”
ヤコブとエサウの母リベカの兄である
Jacob’s parents tell him to travel
to his uncle, Laban,
イサクとリベカはヤコブに
伯父のラバンの所に行って
妻を見つけるようにと言います
to find a wife.
Of course, the core issue
そうするのはもちろん
エサウとのことがあったからです
is the problem with Esau.
思い出してください
Recall that earlier,
Isaac had a problem with the Philistines
イサクとフィリスティア人の間で
トラブルが起きたことがありましたが
—a problem that evidently
could not be settled peacefully.
穏やかに話し合って
解決することはできませんでした
So, what did Isaac do?
イサクはどうしたでしょうか
そこから出ていくことにしました
He moved on.
Now Jacob faces a similar situation.
ヤコブは今 同じような状況にいます
兄のエサウが怒りを募らせています
His brother is seething with anger,
それでヤコブは出ていくことにします
so Jacob leaves.
家族と離れ離れになり
It means leaving his home and his family;
住み慣れた場所を
後にすることになります
it means making a long journey
to a distant land.
遠い地まで長い旅を
しなければいけません
ヤコブは行きたくないと
言うこともできました
Jacob could have chosen to stand his ground.
長男の権利を持っています
He owns the birthright.
「私は77歳になりました
He could argue the matter
with his father and mother:
子供じゃありません」と
言い返すこともできました
‘I’m no child. I’m 77 years old!’
でも決してそうはしませんでした
Jacob does none of those things.
聖書には 「ヤコブが父と母に従って
The Bible simply says:
“Jacob obeyed his father and his mother
パダン･アラムに向かった」
と書かれています
and departed.”
何を学べるでしょうか
What’s the lesson?
私たちも穏やかに話し合えないときが
あるかもしれません
When we face a situation
that can’t be settled peacefully,
ヤコブのように必死で遠くに逃げる
必要はないかもしれません
we probably won’t need to flee for our lives
to a distant land.
とはいえ 場合によっては
Sometimes, however,
it is the course of wisdom
気持ちを抑えて その場から
離れることが大切なときもあります
to walk away from a situation.
格言17章14節にはこうあります
Proverbs 17:14 says:
“Beginning a fight
is like opening a floodgate;
「けんかの始まりは
水門が開く時のようである
言い争いになってしまう前に
そこを去れ」
before the quarrel breaks out,
take your leave.”
ヤコブが伯父の所へ行く途中
While Jacob is on his way to his uncle,
夢の中にエホバが現れます
Jehovah appears to Jacob in a dream
エホバはヤコブのことを
守ると約束します
and assures him
of his support and protection.
でも だからといって
That does not mean
ヤコブの苦労が終わった
わけではありません
that Jacob’s troubles are over.
At the journey’s end,
he moves in with his uncle’s household.
無事に到着し ヤコブは
伯父の所に住み始めます
In time, a situation arises again
やがてそこで また
大変なことが起きます
でもその時も ヤコブは
やはり平和を愛する人でした
that shows that Jacob
is a man who loves peace.
では 創世記29章16節を
開いて 見てみましょう
Let’s read about it from Genesis 29:16.
“Now Laban had two daughters.
ラバンには娘が2人いた
“The name of the older was Leah,
姉はレア 妹はラケルといった
“and the name of the younger, Rachel.
レアは目に輝きがなかったのに対し
“But the eyes of Leah had no luster,
ラケルはとても魅力的な
美しい女性だった
“whereas Rachel had become
“a very attractive and beautiful woman.
ヤコブはラケルを愛するように
なっていたので こう答えた
“Jacob had fallen in love with Rachel,
so he said:
あなたの下の娘ラケルのため
“‘I am willing to serve you seven years
私は喜んであなたに7年仕えます
“for your younger daughter Rachel.’
“To this Laban said:
ラバンは言った
“‘It is better for me to give her to you
than to give her to another man.
あの子をほかの男性と
一緒にならせるより
あなたと一緒にならせる方が
いいと思います
“Keep dwelling with me.’
このままここに住みなさい
“And Jacob served seven years for Rachel,
こうしてヤコブはラケルのために
7年間働いたが
“but in his eyes
they were like just a few days
ラケルを愛していたので
ほんの数日のように思えた
“because of his love for her.
ヤコブはラバンに言った
“Then Jacob said to Laban:
約束の期間が終わりましたので
“‘Give over my wife because my days are up,
彼女と一緒にならせてください
“and let me have relations with her.’
彼女と関係を持たせてください
“With that Laban gathered
all the men of the place
そこでラバンは地元の人たち
皆を集めて宴を催した
“and made a feast.
“But during the evening,
he resorted to taking his daughter Leah
ところがその晩 ラバンは娘のレアを
ヤコブの所に連れていき
“and bringing her to him
that he might have relations with her.
ヤコブがレアと関係を持つようにした
“Laban also gave his female servant Zilpah
ラバンはさらに 自分の召し使いの
女性ジルパをレアの召し使いにした
“to his daughter Leah as a servant.
翌朝 ヤコブが見ると
そこにいたのはレアだった
“In the morning Jacob saw that it was Leah!
それでヤコブはラバンに言った
“So he said to Laban:
何ということをしたのですか
“‘What have you done to me?
私はラケルのために あなたに
仕えたのではなかったでしょうか
“‘Was it not for Rachel that I served you?
“Why have you tricked me?’
どうして私をだましたのですか
“To this Laban said:
ラバンは言った ここの習慣では
“‘It is not our custom here to give
the younger woman before the firstborn.
下の娘を長女より先に
嫁にやることはしません
“‘Celebrate the week of this woman.
祝いの週をあの子と一緒に過ごしなさい
その後 下の子も
妻にすることができます
“‘After that you will also be given
this other woman
“in exchange for serving me
seven more years.’
ただし その代わり
もう7年働いてもらいます
“Jacob did so
and celebrated the week of this woman,
ヤコブは言われた通り 祝いの週を
レアと一緒に過ごした
“after which he gave him
his daughter Rachel as a wife.
その後 ラバンはラケルも
妻としてヤコブに与えた
“Besides, Laban gave
his female servant Bilhah
ラバンはさらに 自分の召し使いの
女性ビルハをラケルの召し使いにした
to his daughter Rachel as her servant.”
ヤコブは怒って当然でした
Jacob has reason to be upset.
ラバンとの約束では 7年間働いた後
He had arranged with Laban
to work seven years for Rachel.
ラケルと結婚して
よいことになっていたからです
At the end of the seven years,
7年がたち 結婚の宴が開かれます
a wedding feast is arranged.
ところが ラバンが連れてきた
ベールで顔を覆われた女性は
But the heavily-veiled woman
brought in to him
is not Rachel;
ラケルではなくレアでした
it’s Leah!
Imagine how shocked Jacob must have been!
ヤコブはどれほどショックを
受けたことでしょう
ラバンは謝るどころかしらを切り
Instead of admitting to his deceit,
Laban gives an excuse.
言い訳をしました
ヤコブはどんなことを
考えたのでしょうか
What thoughts come to Jacob’s mind?
「あなたの子孫は必ず大地の
砂のように多くなる」という約束を
Does he consider that Jehovah
might be working out his promise
エホバが果たそうとしているのかも
しれないと考えたでしょうか
to make Jacob’s offspring plentiful
“like the dust particles of the earth”?
聖書にははっきりとは書かれていません
We don’t know.
でも結果的には レアは
6人の息子を産みました
As it turns out,
Leah bears him six sons,
その中には イスラエルの著名な
2つの部族の祖先となった
including Levi and Judah
—family heads of the two
most honored tribes of Israel.
レビとユダも含まれています
もちろん ヤコブはそうなるとは
知る由もありませんでした
Of course,
Jacob couldn’t have foreknown this.
Still, Jacob the peacemaker
でも平和を愛する人ヤコブは
accepts Leah
レアを受け入れ ラケルのために
もう7年働くようにという
and goes along
with Laban’s outrageous request
ラバンのむちゃくちゃな要求にも
応じることにしました
that he work an additional seven years
for Rachel.
何を学べるでしょうか
What’s the lesson?
約束を破られると
It’s disappointing when others
普通は腹立たしく感じるものです
don’t hold to their agreements.
Like Jacob, can we find it in our hearts
それでも ヤコブのように平和のために
できることはないでしょうか
to forgive and find a way
to preserve peace with them?
どうにかして許すことが
できないでしょうか
Jacob serves Laban
ヤコブは2人の妻のために
for 14 years for his two wives,
14年間ラバンの下で働きました
そして その後も家畜のために
さらに6年働きました
and he works for Laban another 6 years
for a flock of his own.
Finally, at Jehovah’s direction,
ついに エホバから指示があり
子供と妻たち 家畜を全て集め
he gathers his family along with his animals
ラバンには知らせることなく
and, without informing Laban,
he leaves for home.
故郷に向けて旅立ちます
When Laban learns of this, he is furious!
そのことを知ったラバンは激怒します
すぐに後を追い掛け
ヤコブに追い付きます
He chases and catches up with Jacob.
どうなってしまうのでしょうか
This is a dangerous situation,
戦いに発展してもおかしくはありません
one that can easily turn violent.
どうぞ 思い浮かべてみてください
Imagine how it might have been:
ヤコブは今 ギレアデの山地にいます
Jacob had come to a mountainous region.
Possibly it’s morning, and the air is cool.
辺りは 朝の冷たい空気に
包まれています
There are the sounds and smells of animals
羊 ロバ ラクダなど
たくさんの家畜の
鳴き声が聞こえてきます
—sheep, donkeys, camels; there are many.
召し使いたちは 荷物をまとめ
The servants attend to them,
今日一日の旅の支度をしています
getting them ready for the day’s journey.
すると突然 叫び声がします
But then come cries of alarm.
ラバンがやって来たのです
1人ではありません
Laban has come, and he’s not alone.
He arrives with strong men.
武器を持った男たちを引き連れています
They gallop in on camels; they dismount.
ラクダから降りて
こちらに向かってきます
これはただ事ではありません
どうなるのでしょうか
This is not a friendly visit.
ラバンの従者たちは ラバンからの
指示を待っています
Laban’s men are ready
to obey orders from Laban.
ヤコブの従者たちも
何事かと集まってきます
Jacob’s servants quickly gather to the scene.
その場にいるみんなの視線が
All eyes are fixed on Laban and Jacob,
向かい合っているラバンとヤコブに
向けられます
who argue.
その前の晩 ラバンは
夢の中に出てきたエホバから
The previous night,
Jehovah had warned Laban in a dream
ヤコブを困らせるようなことは
言わないようにと言われていました
to be careful about what he’d say to Jacob.
それでも ラバンは怒りのままに
Still, Laban is angry and aggressive.
ヤコブに食って掛かります
Laban makes two charges.
ラバンはまずこう言って
ヤコブを責め立てます
First, he says:
“Why have you resorted to outwitting me
「何ということをしてくれたのですか
どうして私に黙って
“and carrying my daughters off like captives
娘たちを捕虜のようにして
連れ去ったのですか
“taken by the sword?
“Why did you run away secretly
どうして何も言わずに
こっそり逃げていったのですか」
and outwit me and not tell me?”
The answer to that charge is obvious.
そう言われて ヤコブは
素直にこう答えます
Jacob replies:
“It was because I was afraid,
「あなたが娘たちを私から力ずくで
奪うのではないかと思い
“for I said to myself,
‘You might take your daughters
away from me by force.’”
恐れたのです」
ラバンはさらに テラフィム像を
盗んだと言ってヤコブを責めます
Laban also charges that Jacob has stolen
his household gods.
たしかに ラケルが像を
持ち出していましたが
Rachel has indeed stolen the gods,
ヤコブはそのことを
全く知りませんでした
but Jacob knows nothing about this.
ラバンは探しますが
見つけることはできませんでした
A search is made,
but the idols are not found.
そこでヤコブは自分の考えを伝えます
Jacob then makes his defense.
Let’s take up our reading
創世記31章36節
開いて 見てみましょう
at Genesis 31:36.
それでヤコブは怒って
ラバンを責めるようになり
“At that Jacob became angry
ラバンにこう言った
私にどんな過ちがあるのですか
“and began to criticize Laban.
“Jacob then said to Laban:
私がどんな罪を犯したというので
私の後を激しく追ってきたのですか
“‘What is my offense, and for what sin
are you hotly pursuing me?
あなたは私の持ち物を全部調べました
“‘Now that you have searched
through all my goods,
あなたの家の物が何かありましたか
“‘what have you found
that belongs to your house?
それをここに 私の兄弟たちと
あなたの兄弟たちの前に出してください
“‘Put it here in front of my brothers
and your brothers,
“‘and let them decide between the two of us.
あなたと私のどちらが正しいのかを
決めてもらいましょう
“‘During these 20 years
that I have been with you,
私があなたの所で過ごしてきた
この20年の間
“‘your sheep and your goats never miscarried,
あなたの羊とヤギが
流産したことはありませんでした
“‘and I never ate the rams of your flock.
私があなたの群れの雄羊を
食べたこともありません
“‘I did not bring you any animal
torn by wild beasts.
私は 野獣に引き裂かれた家畜を
あなたの所に持っていくことはせず
“‘I would stand the loss of it myself.
“‘Whether the animal was stolen by day
or was stolen by night,
自分でその損失を負いました
家畜が昼に盗まれても夜に盗まれても
“‘you would demand compensation from me.
あなたは私に弁償を求めました
“‘By day the heat consumed me,
and the cold by night,
私は 昼の暑さと夜の寒さに苦しめられ
“‘and sleep would flee from my eyes.
眠ることさえできませんでした
“‘This makes 20 years for me in your house.
私はあなたの所で
20年間過ごしてきました
“‘I have served you 14 years
for your two daughters
あなたの2人の娘のために14年
あなたの家畜のために6年働いたのです
“‘and 6 years for your flock,
“‘and you kept changing my wages ten times.
しかも あなたは報酬を
10回も変えました
“‘If the God of my father, the God of Abraham
もし私の父祖の神 アブラハムの神で
イサクが畏れる方が
“‘and the One whom Isaac fears,
“‘had not been on my side,
私の側にいてくださらなかったなら
“‘you would now have sent me away
empty-handed.
あなたは私に何も持たせずに
去らせたでしょう
“‘God has seen my affliction
and the toil of my hands,
神は 私の苦悩と苦労を見て
“and that is why he reproved you last night.’
昨夜あなたを戒められました
ラバンはヤコブに答えた
“Then Laban answered Jacob:
娘は私の娘 子供は私の子供
“‘The daughters are my daughters
and the children my children
“‘and the flock my flock,
家畜は私の家畜です
“‘and everything you are looking at
あなたが見ているものは全部
“‘is mine and my daughters’.
私と私の娘たちのものです
“‘What can I do today against these
or against their children
娘と娘が産んだ子供に対して
私は悪いことを行えるでしょうか
“‘whom they have borne?
“‘Now come, let us make a covenant,
you and I,
さあ あなたと私の間で
契約を結びましょう
“and it will serve as a witness between us.’
それがあなたと私の間の証人となります
“So Jacob took a stone
and set it up as a pillar.
そこでヤコブは石を1つ取り
記念碑として立てた
“Then Jacob said to his brothers:
‘Pick up stones!’
それから兄弟たちに
石を拾ってきてください！ と言った
“And they took stones and made a pile.
兄弟たちは石を拾い 積んで山にした
“After that they ate there
on the pile of stones.
そして一同はその山の所で食事をした
“And Laban began calling it Jegarsahadutha,
ラバンはその山を
エガル･サハドタと呼び
“but Jacob called it Galeed.
ヤコブはガルエドと呼んだ
“Laban then said:
ラバンは言った 今日 この石の山は
“‘This pile of stones is a witness
私とあなたの間の証人です
“between me and you today.’
それでその山はガルエドと名付けられた
“That is why he named it Galeed,
and the Watchtower,
また 見張り台とも呼ばれた
“for he said:
ラバンがこう言ったからである
“‘Let Jehovah keep watch between you and me
私たちが離れている時も
“‘when we are out of each other’s sight.
エホバがあなたと私を
見守っていてくださいますように
“‘If you mistreat my daughters
もしあなたが私の娘たちを
むごく扱ったり
“‘and if you start taking wives
in addition to my daughters,
娘たちのほかに妻を迎えたりするなら
“‘though there is no man with us,
たとえ人が見ていなくても
“remember that God will be a witness
between you and me.’
あなたと私の証人である神は見ています
“Laban went on to say to Jacob:
そのことを忘れないでください
ラバンはさらにヤコブに言った
“‘Here is this pile of stones,
ここに石の山と 私があなたとの間に
立てた記念碑があります
“‘and here is the pillar
that I have erected between you and me.
“‘This pile of stones is a witness,
この石の山は証人であり
記念碑も証人です
“‘and the pillar
is something that bears witness,
私はこの石の山を越えてあなたに
害を加えることはなく
“‘that I will not pass beyond this pile
of stones to bring harm to you
あなたもこの石の山と記念碑を越えて
私に害を加えることはありません
“‘and you will not pass
beyond this pile of stones
“‘and this pillar to bring harm to me.
アブラハムの神 ナホルの神
“‘Let the God of Abraham
and the God of Nahor,
彼らの父の神が 私たちを
裁かれますように
“the God of their father, judge between us.’
それでヤコブは 父イサクが
畏れる方に懸けて誓った
“And Jacob swore by the One
“whom his father Isaac fears.
その後ヤコブは山で犠牲を捧げ
“After that Jacob offered
a sacrifice in the mountain
パンを食べるよう兄弟たちを招いた
“and invited his brothers to eat bread.
それで彼らは食べ 山で夜を過ごした
“So they ate
and spent the night in the mountain.
ラバンは朝早く起きて
自分の孫や娘たちに口づけし
“However, Laban got up early in the morning
“and kissed his grandchildren
and his daughters and blessed them.
彼らのために祝福を願い求めた
それから自分の家へ帰っていった
Then Laban departed and returned home.”
Jacob had served Laban faithfully
for 20 years,
ヤコブはラバンのために
20年間ひたすら働きました
ラバンにいいように使われ
だまされてもそうしました
even though Laban had defrauded
and exploited him.
ラバンは自分の非を認めません
Laban doesn’t acknowledge that
but, rather, dishonestly claims
それどころか ヤコブの
妻も子供も家畜も
that he is the rightful owner
全部自分のものだと言い張ったのです
of all that Jacob has with him.
そしてラバンは 平和のための
契約を結ぼうと提案します
Laban then suggests
that they make a covenant of peace
今後ずっと お互いに害を
加えることはしないという約束です
ensuring that neither family
will bring harm to the other.
ラバンは 平和を愛していたので
そう言ったわけではありません
Laban’s motive is not that he loves peace.
It might have been to ensure
that Jacob will not return
自分の死後 ヤコブに
息子たちの相続地を
奪われるのではないかと
心配になったのかもしれません
with the household gods after Laban’s death
テラフィム像を持っている人には
to deprive his sons of their inheritance.
そうする権利があると
考えられていたからです
In any case, Jacob agrees;
いずれにしても ヤコブは
契約を結ぶことにしました
everyone relaxes;
緊張は和らぎ 争いには
ならずに済みました
there’s to be no violence.
And a monument is set up
to memorialize the agreement.
合意の印として記念碑が建てられました
20年もひどい扱いを
受けたにもかかわらず
Despite the many years of oppression,
ヤコブは平和の契約を
結ぶことに同意しました
Jacob agrees to a covenant of peace.
He does not harbor resentment
or seek revenge.
恨みを抱くことも 復讐することも
決してしませんでした
That crisis is over for Jacob.
このことはこれで一件落着しました
でも また別の心配なことが生じます
But now another one looms.
Jacob sends messengers to his brother.
ヤコブは兄エサウの所に
使者を遣わします
そうやって エサウに会いに
行こうとしていること
They say that Jacob is returning
and that he seeks Esau’s favor.
仲直りしたいと思っていることを
伝えます
The messengers return with the news
that Esau is on his way to meet him
使者が戻ってきてこう報告します
エサウはこちらに向かってきていて
and with him are 400 men.
400人もの男たちを引き連れています
なんてことでしょう
Oh, my!
エサウはまだ怒っているのでしょうか
Is Esau still angry?
Understandably, Jacob is worried.
ヤコブは不安でいっぱいになります
He does not want to fight with his brother.
自分の兄エサウと戦いたくはありません
Let us see how he handles the situation.
ヤコブは一体どうするでしょうか
創世記32章13節を開いて
見てみましょう
Please turn to Genesis 32:13.
“And he spent the night there.
ヤコブはそこで夜を過ごした
“Then he took some of his possessions
そして 自分の家畜の中から
兄エサウへの贈り物を選んだ
“as a gift for Esau his brother:
“200 female goats, 20 male goats,
雌ヤギ200匹 雄ヤギ20匹
雌羊200匹 雄羊20匹
“200 female sheep, 20 rams,
子に乳を飲ませているラクダ30頭
“30 camels nursing their young,
“40 cows, 10 bulls,
雌牛40頭 雄牛10頭
“20 female donkeys
雌ロバ20頭 雄ロバ10頭である
“and 10 full-grown male donkeys.
“He handed them over to his servants,
ヤコブはそれらを群れごとに
召し使いたちに託し こう言った
“one drove after another,
“and he said to his servants:
私より先に渡りなさい
“‘Cross over ahead of me,
群れと群れとの間に距離を置きなさい
“and you are to set a space
between one drove and the next.’
さらに 先頭の人にこう命じた
“He also commanded the first one:
私の兄エサウがあなたと会い
“‘In case Esau my brother
should meet you and ask,
「主人は誰か あなたはどこへ行くのか
“‘“To whom do you belong,
and where are you going,
前を行く家畜は誰のものか」と
尋ねてきたなら こう言いなさい
“‘and to whom do these ahead of you belong?”
“‘then you should say,
“To your servant Jacob.
「主人はヤコブでございます
“‘“It is a gift sent to my lord, to Esau,
これはエサウ様への贈り物です
“and look! he himself is also behind us.”’
ヤコブも後から参ります」
“And he commanded also the second, the third,
ヤコブはまた 2番目の人 3番目の人
“and all those following the droves:
家畜の群れの後を行く人
全てにこう命じた
“‘According to this word,
“‘you are to speak to Esau when you meet him.
あなたたちも エサウに会ったなら
同じことを話しなさい
“‘And you should also say,
そして 「ヤコブは後から参ります」
と言いなさい
““Here is your servant Jacob behind us.”’
“For he said to himself:
ヤコブは 贈り物を
先に送ってなだめれば
“‘If I appease him
by sending a gift ahead of me,
私と会った時に優しく迎えてくれる
かもしれない と思ったのである
“‘then afterward when I see him,
he may give me a kindly reception.’”
平和を愛する人ヤコブは
Jacob wants peaceful relations
with his brother.
兄のエサウと仲直りしたい
と思っています
He sends a generous gift
—hundreds of animals—
それで そのためにたくさんの
贈り物をします
to help make that possible.
何百もの家畜です
Was Jacob weak-minded,
ヤコブは気が弱くて 兄のエサウに
おびえていたのでしょうか
too cowardly to stand up to his brother?
そんなことはありません
Not at all!
なぜなら これから
エサウに会うという時に
Why, as the time neared
for the meeting with Esau,
Jacob wrestles with an angel until dawn
ヤコブはエホバからの祝福を求めて
天使と明け方まで
取っ組み合いをしたからです
to receive further assurance
of Jehovah’s blessing.
Let’s now see what happens
when the two brothers meet.
では ヤコブとエサウは
どんな再会をしたのでしょうか
創世記33章1節を開いて
見てみましょう
Please turn to Genesis 33:1.
“Now Jacob raised his eyes
ヤコブが目を上げると
エサウが400人の人たちと
一緒に来るのが見えた
“and saw Esau coming,
“and 400 men were with him.
そこでヤコブは レアとラケルと
召し使いの女性2人に
“So he divided the children
among Leah, Rachel,
それぞれの子供たちを託した
“and the two female servants.
前方に召し使いの女性たちと
その子供たちを
“He put the female servants
and their children in front,
その後ろにレアとその子供たちを
“Leah and her children after them,
その後ろにラケルとヨセフを配置した
“and Rachel and Joseph behind them.
そしてヤコブ自身は先頭に立って進み
“Then he himself went ahead of them
自分の兄に近づくまでに7回ひれ伏した
“and bowed down to the earth seven times
“as he came near to his brother.
するとエサウはヤコブに走り寄り
“But Esau ran to meet him,
抱き締めて口づけした
“and he embraced him and kissed him,
2人は泣きだした
“and they burst into tears.
エサウは女性や子供たちの
方を見ると こう言った
“When he raised his eyes
and saw the women and the children,
あなたと一緒にいる
この人たちは誰ですか
“he said: ‘Who are these with you?’
ヤコブは言った
“To which he said:
神が私に授けてくださった
子供たちでございます
“‘The children with whom God
has favored your servant.’
その時 召し使いの女性たちが
“At that the female servants
came forward with their children
子供たちと一緒に前に出てきて
ひれ伏した
“and bowed down,
そして レアも子供たちと一緒に
前に出てきて ひれ伏した
“and Leah too came forward with her children,
“and they bowed down.
それから ヨセフがラケルと一緒に
前に出てきて ひれ伏した
“Then Joseph came forward with Rachel,
“and they bowed down.
エサウは言った
“Esau said:
どうして私の所に 人と家畜の
群れを来させたのですか
“‘What is the purpose of all this camp
of travelers that I have met?’
ヤコブは答えた お兄さまの好意を
得たいと思ったからです
“He replied: ‘In order to find favor
“in the eyes of my lord.’
エサウは言った 弟よ 私は非常に
たくさんの物を持っています
“Then Esau said:
“‘I have a great many possessions,
my brother.
だから あなたの物は
そのままにしておきなさい
“Keep what is yours.’
“However, Jacob said:
ヤコブは言った
いいえ お願いです
“‘No, please.
もし私のことを良く思って
くださっているのでしたら
“‘If I have found favor in your eyes,
あなたの顔を見るために
持ってきたこの贈り物を
“‘you must take my gift from my hand,
私の手からぜひ受け取ってください
“‘because I brought it
so that I could see your face.
あなたの顔を見た時
“‘And I have seen your face
神の顔を見ているようでした
私のことを喜んで
迎えてくださったからです
“‘as though seeing God’s face,
“‘in that you received me with pleasure.
心を込めた贈り物をお持ちしました
“‘Take, please,
“‘the gift conveying my blessing
that was brought to you,
どうか受け取ってください
神が恵みを与えてくださり
“‘for God has favored me
私は必要な物を全て持っています
“and I have everything I need.’
ヤコブがしきりに勧めたので
And he continued to urge him,
so that he took it.”
エサウは贈り物を受け取った
What a happy outcome!
本当に良かったですね
Instead of an angry confrontation,
怒りをぶつけ合うのではなく
喜びの再会となりました
there is a joyful reunion.
2人は涙を流し 抱き締め合いました
The two men shed tears; they embrace.
Again, Jacob is the peacemaker.
この度も ヤコブは平和をつくりました
How did he prove that?
どのようにしてでしょうか
祈りました そして
祈りに沿って行動しました
He prayed, and he acted in harmony
with his prayers.
He sent gifts.
贈り物をし エサウのことを
お兄様と呼び
He showed honor and respect to his brother,
calling him lord
7回もひれ伏して敬意を表したのです
and bowing seven times.
What’s the lesson?
何を学べるでしょうか
Doesn’t this account well illustrate
クリスチャンの仲間との
平和を守るために
the extent to which we
should be willing to go
私たちがどれほどのことを
すべきかについて
to preserve peace
with our Christian brothers and sisters?
考えさせられるのではないでしょうか
私たちも平和を守るために
できるだけのことをしたいと思います
We learn so much
about seeking peace from Jacob.
When threatened by his brother
while living at home,
ヤコブはエサウが激怒した時には
自分から家を出ていきました
he moved away.
When deceived by Laban
regarding Rachel and Leah,
ラケルとレアのことで
ラバンからだまされた時も
事を荒立てませんでした
he yielded.
追い掛けてきたラバンに
責め立てられた時も
When chased down and accused by Laban,
平和の契約を結ぶことに同意しました
Jacob agreed to a covenant of peace.
エサウに再会する時も贈り物をしました
And when confronting Esau, he offered a gift.
考えてみてください
Keep in mind,
in none of these situations
どの時をとってもヤコブに非が
あったわけではありません
was Jacob the one who needed to apologize.
でも いつどんな時も
Yet, throughout his life,
Jacob loved peace.
ヤコブは平和を愛しました
He relied on Jehovah,
エホバを信頼し続け
エホバは応えてくれました
and Jehovah blessed him.
エホバはヤコブをよく見ていました
Jehovah never forgot Jacob
いつも平和のために頑張る姿を見て
and how he pursued peace
in his dealings with others.
ほほ笑んでいたことでしょう
When we do the same
同じように 私たちも
誰かからひどい扱いを受けたり
—when we pursue peace
in the face of injustice,
迫害を受けたりしても
平和のために頑張るなら
in the face of persecution,
たとえ小さなことであれ
大きなことであれそうするなら
in small issues as well as in big issues—
エホバは私たちを見て
ほほ笑んでくれます
Jehovah will not forget us either.
Jehovah will richly bless us
必ず幸せにしてくれます
if we love peace
ヤコブがしたのと同じように
just as Jacob loved peace.
平和を愛するならば
How comforting it is
平和をつくる人をエホバが愛し
支えてくれることを考えると
to reflect on Jehovah’s love and support
本当に励みになるのではないでしょうか
for those who make peace!
This Bible account is filled
with practical examples
今注目した聖書の部分には
私たちが倣える良い手本が
たくさん含まれています
that each of us can imitate.
うれしいことに 今楽しんだ
You will be pleased to know
that the dramatic Bible reading
劇形式の聖書朗読
「ヤコブ 平和を愛した人」は
“Jacob—A Man Who Loved Peace”
is now available for download
jw.orgと JW Library®アプリで
ダウンロードすることができます
on the jw.org website
and in the JW Library® {
どうぞお聞きください
How can we maintain our God-given peace
神への敬意がない世の中で
どうすれば神からの平和を
失わずに済むでしょうか
despite living in an ungodly world?
Please pay close attention
教育委員会の援助者
デービッド・シェーファー兄弟が
to Brother David Schafer,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
その疑問に答えてくださいますので
注意深く聞きましょう
as he answers this question in the talk
話の主題は 「真の正しさは
平和をもたら［す］」です
“The Result of True Righteousness
Will Be Peace.”
先ほどフィリピ 4:7にある
Earlier, we considered
the expression at Philippians 4:7,
「人間の理解をはるかに超え」た
「神からの平和」について考えました
“the peace of God
that surpasses all understanding,”
私たちはエホバとの
親しい関係があるので
that is, the tranquility and calmness
we enjoy because we have
a close friendship with Jehovah.
穏やかで落ち着いていることができます
What a remarkable blessing!
素晴らしい祝福です
But although we enjoy God-given peace,
私たちは神からの平和を得ていますが
our life in this system of things
is not problem free, is it?
今の体制の生活には
問題が付きものではないでしょうか
Psalm 34:19 acknowledges
as much when it says:
詩編 34:19にはこうあります
“Many are the hardships of the righteous one,
「正しい人は多くの苦難に遭う
but Jehovah rescues him from them all.”
しかし エホバがその全てから
助け出してくださる」
家族の反対や迫害 戦争 自然災害
We may experience family opposition,
persecution, war, natural disasters,
重い病気などの苦難を経験するとしても
or severe illnesses,
but none of these hardships
can “separate us from God’s love.”
どれも「神の愛から私たちを
引き離すことはできません」
“Neither death nor life nor angels
「死も 生も 天使も 政府も
今あるものも これから来るものも」
nor governments
nor things now here nor things to come”
—none of these things
can rob us of the peace Jehovah gives.
どんなものもエホバが与えてくださる
平和を奪うことはできません
とはいえ その平和を
奪うものもあります
And yet, there is something that can.
イザヤ 32:17を開いて
Please turn with me to Isaiah 32:17.
ご一緒に読みましょう
And as we read this text,
その聖句は 平和が
notice that it refers to peace as a result.
あるものの結果であることを
明らかにしています
Do you think of peace that way, as a result?
平和についてそう考えた
ことがありますか
平和という結果をもたらすのは
何でしょうか
If peace is a result, what causes it?
Isaiah 32:17:
イザヤ 32:17
“The result
こうあります
“of true righteousness will be peace,
「真の正しさは平和をもたらし
“and the fruitage of true righteousness
絶えることのない
平穏と安心を生み出す」
will be lasting tranquility and security.”
「絶えることのない
平穏と安心」とあります
本当に魅力的で
What a beautiful expression,
“lasting tranquility and security”!
美しい表現ではありませんか
何が平和をもたらしますか
Again, from what does it result?
真の正しさです
True righteousness.
What if righteousness
no longer mattered to us?
何が正しいかを気に掛けなくなったら
どうなりますか
What if a person concluded:
‘It makes no difference
「どう生きようと どんな犠牲を
払おうと何も変わらない
‘how I live or what sacrifices I make.
結局 つらい目に遭うんだから
できる時に自分のしたいことを
‘I’m going to suffer hardships either way.
I might as well do
whatever I please while I can’?
何でもした方がいい」とある人は
考えるかもしれません
What’s wrong with that thinking?
それは何が間違っていますか
Would it show appreciation for peace
平和とそのためにエホバがしてくれた
ことへの感謝がありません
and all that Jehovah
has done to make it possible?
Peace is a result.
平和は結果です
結果には必ず原因があります
And behind every result is a cause.
If we want peace,
we have to pursue righteousness.
平和を望むなら 平和を
追い求めなければなりません
An unrighteous person
cannot be at peace with God.
正しくない人に神との平和はありません
Serious transgressions put a strain
on a person’s relationship with God.
重大な罪を犯すと
神との関係に影響が及びます
詩編 38:3のダビデ王の言葉を
思い出してください
Recall King David’s words found
at Psalm 38:3.
Sensing Jehovah’s disapproval, he wrote:
エホバの恵みを失ったと感じ
“There is no peace
「私が罪を犯したので私の内に
安らぎはない」と言っています
within my bones because of my sin.”
正しくない人は まいたものを
必ず刈り取り
Inevitably, the unrighteous person
will reap what he sows and lose his peace.
平和を失ってしまうのです
正しさとは何ですか
What is righteousness,
and how do we pursue it?
どのように追い求められますか
Righteousness is what we have or what we show
正しさを示すには エホバの基準に
従って正しいことを行う必要があります
when we do what is right
according to Jehovah’s standards.
その基準は単なる規則ではなく原則で
And those standards
are not just rules we follow
but principles that guide the way
we deal with each other.
互いへの接し方に影響します
As Universal Sovereign and Creator,
何が正しいかを決めるのは 宇宙の
主権者で創造者であるエホバ神です
Jehovah God determines what is righteous.
Isn’t that what was represented
エデンの園の「善悪の知識の木」が
そのことを表していました
by “the tree of the knowledge
of good and bad” in the garden of Eden?
As a result of Jehovah’s command
to abstain from its fruit,
エホバはその木の実を
食べてはならないと命令します
that tree represented God’s right
to determine for his creatures
その木は 創造物にとって
何が善で何が悪かを決める
what is good and what is bad for them.
神の権利を表していました
And although Jehovah
has given humans free will,
エホバは人間に自由意思
選択する権利を与えましたが
the right to choose,
完全な人間にさえ
何が正しくて何が正しくないか
he has not granted humans
(not even perfect ones)
the right to set the standard
for what is righteous and what is not.
基準を定める権利は与えませんでした
イザヤ 32:17を
もう一度見てください
Now, notice once again that Isaiah 32:17 says
冒頭にこうありました
「真の正しさ」
that “the result
of true righteousness will be peace.”
正しさといっても2種類あります
It uses that term twice—“true righteousness.”
本当に正しいものと
正しく見えるだけのものです
Not everything called righteousness
is true righteousness.
Many people view righteousness
as just a personal virtue
多くの人にとって 正しいとは
規則を守るという程度のことです
achieved by following the rules.
At Matthew 23:28,
マタイ 23:28でイエスは
パリサイ派の人は
Jesus said that the Pharisees
appeared righteous on the outside,
外側は正しく見えても
内側はそうではないと言いました
but inside they were lawless.
伝道の書 7:16で
述べられている人は
Ecclesiastes 7:16 talks about those
自分の基準は神の基準よりも
正しいと考えます
who think their standards
are more righteous even than God’s.
And at Romans 10:3,
ローマ 10:3でパウロは
Paul talked about people
who ‘seek to establish
「何が正しいかを自分たちで決めようと
した」人たちについて述べています
their own righteousness.’
でも 見せ掛けの正しさや
But false piety,
over-righteousness, and self-righteousness
行き過ぎた正しさ 独善的な正しさは
are not what Isaiah 32:17 is talking about.
イザヤ 32:17が
述べているものではありません
今では エホバが禁じる行為を
Today, many argue for the acceptance
何も悪いことではないと
主張する人たちがいます
of conduct that Jehovah forbids.
They may even find support
from a world already alienated from God.
神に従わない世の中の
ほかの人たちも
それに同意しています
But wide acceptance in a growing community
でも 広く受け入れられて
いるからといって
正しいことにはなりません
does not redefine righteousness.
それは真の正しさではありません
None of that is true righteousness.
何が正しいか基準を定めるのは
愛のある創造者です
Our loving Creator sets
the standard for what is right
私たちや一般の人が
どう感じるかではありません
—not our feelings,
not the community at large.
Now, while you’re here in Isaiah,
まだイザヤを開いている間に
48章をご覧ください
please turn to chapter 48.
正しい人と見なされるには
In order to be viewed as righteous,
we have to trust that Jehovah
何が正しいかの基準を定めるのは
エホバであることを
認めなければなりません
should set the standard of right and wrong.
In addition, we must prove
by our speech and actions
さらに エホバの基準に同意している
ことを言葉と行動で示し
that we agree with Jehovah’s standards
and obey him.
エホバに従わなければなりません
And that takes real courage
in a wicked world.
邪悪な世界でそうするのは
本当に勇気が必要です
でも そうするなら
結果として平和を味わえることを
But when we do that, we enjoy the result.
Notice what it says at Isaiah chapter 48,
イザヤ 48:17, 18は
こう述べています
verses 17, 18:
“This is what Jehovah says, your Repurchaser,
「あなたを救う方
イスラエルの聖なる方
“the Holy One of Israel:
エホバはこう言う
“‘I, Jehovah, am your God,
『私エホバは あなたの神である
“‘the One teaching you to benefit yourself
あなたのためになる生き方を教え
“‘[or as the footnote says, teaching you
“for your own good”],
［「あなたのためになる生き方」です］
“‘the One guiding you
in the way you should walk.
あなたを導いて正しい道を歩ませる
“‘If only you would pay attention
to my commandments!
あなたが私のおきてに
注意を払いさえすれば！
そうすれば あなたの平和は
川の流れのように豊かになり
“‘Then your peace
would become just like a river
and your righteousness
like the waves of the sea.’”
あなたの正しい行いは
海の波のように多くなる』」
エホバのおきてに注意を払うなら
良いことが2つあります
Paying attention to Jehovah’s commandments
results in two things.
First, our peace
まず 平和が「川の流れのように」
will “become just like a river”
穏やかに 豊かに ずっと続きます
—serene, abundant, ongoing.
そして 正しい行いが
「海の波のように」多くなります
Second, our righteousness
will be “like the waves of the sea.”
Remember your last trip to the beach?
イメージしてみてください
As you stood there on the shore,
あなたが海辺に もしかすると
丘の上に立って
perhaps on a high hill overlooking the ocean
海を眺めていると
波が寄せては打ち返します
watching the waves
roll in one after the other
それが何千年も繰り返されてきました
just as they have for thousands of years,
could you feel a sense of constancy?
ずっと続いていくように感じられます
Jehovah says that our course
エホバは私たちの正しい行いが
of doing what is right can be just like that.
まさにそのようになると言っています
私たちを導いて正しい道を歩ませ
He will guide us
in the path of righteousness.
He will bless us with unending peace.
終わりのない平和を与えてくださいます
In the process, we learn through experience
そのようにして 私たちは経験を通して
how Jehovah’s wise and loving ways
愛と知恵のあるエホバの教える生き方が
本当にためになることを理解します
truly benefit us personally.
But if we refuse to do that,
正しいことを行わないなら
動揺や混乱を経験します
we learn what agitation
and discord truly mean.
22節にはこうあります
As verse 22 says:
“‘There is no peace,’ says Jehovah,
‘for the wicked.’”
「『邪悪な者たちに平和はない』と
エホバは言う」
これは人間への脅しではありません
It’s not a heavy-handed threat to manipulate
human behavior
as if Jehovah needed to do that.
エホバはそうする必要などありません
It’s a fact, a truth, a timeless principle.
これは事実 不変の真理です
“God is love.”
「神は愛」です
その教えは私たちのためです
He teaches us for our own good.
And the result if we pay attention is peace
注意を払うことの結果は 平和です
—Isaiah 48:17, 18.
イザヤ 48:17, 18
And these verses assure us
that imperfect humans
この聖句は 不完全な人間であっても
truly can have a righteous standing with God.
神から正しいと見ていただける
ということを保証しています
Let’s explore that further.
さらに考えましょう
Do you recall the very first time
「正しい」という言葉が
最初に聖書に出てくるのは
どこかご存じですか
the word “righteous” is used in the Bible?
Turn with me, please, to Genesis chapter 6.
ご一緒に創世記 6章を開きましょう
Now, you likely recognize this
as the account about Noah.
お気付きの通り ノアに関する記述です
Noah lived in an extremely wicked world.
ノアはとても邪悪な世界に
生きていました
During his lifetime, rebel angels
left their assignments in heaven,
反逆した天使が天の居場所を
離れて人間の姿になり
materialized, married human women,
人間の女性と結婚し
and fathered hybrid offspring
who became violent giants.
生まれてきた子は
乱暴な巨人になりました
Now, how did all of that wickedness
and violence affect Jehovah?
悪と暴力があふれているのを見て
エホバはどう感じたでしょうか
According to Genesis 6:6,
創世記 6:6にはこうあります
“his heart was saddened,”
「エホバは⋯⋯悲しんだ」
which is a remarkable thing to contemplate,
isn’t it?
考えてみると
すごいことではありませんか
私たちの決定がエホバの気持ちに
影響を与えるのです
Jehovah’s feelings are affected
by our decisions because he cares for us.
エホバは私たちに
関心を持っているからです
That ancient world became so wicked
その古代の世界が
あまりに邪悪だったので
that Jehovah decided it must be destroyed.
エホバは滅ぼすことに決めました
And yet, right in the midst
of all this depravity,
でも そうした堕落した世界の中で
ノアは違っていました
Noah showed a different spirit.
創世記 6:8, 9を読みましょう
Notice what it says at Genesis 6:8, 9:
“But Noah found favor in the eyes of Jehovah.
「しかし ノアはエホバからの
好意を得ていた
“This is the history of Noah.
以下はノアについての記録である
Noah was a righteous man.”
ノアは正しい人で」
出てきましたね ノアが正しい人と
言われているのはなぜですか
There it is.
And why was he described as righteous?
“He proved himself faultless
「当時の人々とは異なり
非の打ちどころがない人だった」
among his contemporaries.”
Yes, Noah was not like the rebel angels
ノアは 反逆した天使やその子たち
or their offspring
or like degraded human society.
堕落した人間たちとは
異なっていたのです
“Noah walked with the true God.”
「ノアは真の神と共に歩んだ」
And thus the second time
we find the word “righteous”
「正しい」という言葉が
次に聖書に出てくるのは
is at Genesis 7:1:
創世記 7:1です
“After that, Jehovah said to Noah:
このように書かれています
“‘Go into the ark,
you and all your household,
「やがてエホバはノアに言った
『あなたとあなたの家族は皆
箱船に入りなさい
“‘because you are the one
“‘I have found to be righteous
あなたがこの世代の人々とは違って
before me among this generation.’”
正しい人であることを私は知った』」
ノアは正しい人だったので
Because of Noah’s righteousness,
家族と共に洪水を生き延び
he and his family survived the Flood
to worship Jehovah on a cleansed earth.
エホバへの崇拝を続けました
And after the waters subsided
洪水の水が引くと
and the family emerged from the ark,
家族は箱船から出て
they witnessed a splendid sight,
素晴らしい光景を目にします
one never before observed:
初めて見る光景です
a serene, multicolored arch
空に穏やかな7色の帯が見えます
in the sky
—a rainbow—
虹です 神との平和を示す
確かなしるしです
a reassuring indication
of peace with God,
そうです 正しさは平和をもたらします
peace resulting from righteousness.
聖書で「正しい人」という言葉は
次にどこに出てきますか
And where does the word “righteous”
appear next in the Bible?
In the account about Abraham
アブラハムに関する記述
創世記 18章に記されている
—notably in his famous conversation
with Jehovah
エホバとのあの有名な会話です
found in Genesis chapter 18,
where Jehovah promised Abraham
that if he found
エホバはアブラハムに ソドムの町に
正しい人が10人でもいるなら
as few as ten righteous people
in the city of Sodom,
その町を滅ぼさないと約束しました
he would not destroy that city.
Now, what was it that distinguished Abraham
アブラハムが周りの人たちとは違って
正しいと見なされたのはなぜですか
as righteous in that moral climate?
As you read Genesis chapters 12 through 22,
創世記 12章から22章を
読んでいくと分かる通り
you get the sense that Abraham
アブラハムは強くて
揺るぎない信仰を持っていました
was a man of great faith, unwavering faith.
エホバから求められることを
何でも行おうとしました
He was ready to do whatever
Jehovah asked of him.
Now, citing Genesis 15:6
創世記 15:6などの聖句を基にして
and other texts, James 2:23 says
ヤコブ 2:23はこう言っています
that “‘Abraham put faith in Jehovah,
「『アブラハムはエホバに信仰を持ち
“‘and it was counted to him
そのことは正しいと見なされた』
という聖句の通りになり
“as righteousness,’
“and he came to be called Jehovah’s friend
アブラハムはエホバの友と
呼ばれるようになったのです」
“[Jehovah’s friend,
正しさが神との平和をもたらし
“peace with God resulting
エホバの友となったのです
from righteousness].”
Now, what about God’s people today?
いま神に仕えている人たちはどうですか
Turn with me, please, to Isaiah chapter 60
イザヤ 60章をどうぞお開きください
—Isaiah chapter 60.
イザヤ 60章です
Jehovah refers to Noah
エホバはノアとアブラハムについて
and Abraham as “righteous.”
「正しい」と言いました
But what would he say about you and me?
では私たちについてはどうでしょうか
Well, notice what it says
toward the end of this chapter.
その章の最後の2つの節に
注目しましょう
Isaiah chapter 60,
60:21, 22です
verses 21, 22:
“And all your people
「あなたの民は皆 正しいことを行い
“will be righteous;
“they will possess the land forever.
土地を永遠に所有する
彼らは 私が栄光を受けるように
“They are the sprout that I planted,
私が植えた苗
私が形作った者たちである
“the work of my hands,
for me to be beautified.
“The little one will become a thousand
and the small one a mighty nation.
小さな者が千人にもなり
取るに足りない者が強大な国民になる
“I myself, Jehovah,
私エホバが 定めの時にそれを速める」
will speed it up in its own time.”
Yes, prospective members of the great crowd
大群衆になる見込みを持つ人たちが
アブラハムのように神の友として
have been declared righteous
as friends of God as Abraham was.
正しいと認められています
In Jehovah’s eyes, they are, as it says
エホバから見て その人たちは
啓示 7:9にあるように
in Revelation 7:9, “dressed in white robes.”
「白くて長い衣服を着て」います
そして 聖なる力によって選ばれ
Today, they’re serving
alongside God’s spirit-anointed ones
正しいと認められた人たちと
共に奉仕しています
who are declared righteous for life.
“Jehovah, [our] Repurchaser,
私たちを「救う方 イスラエルの
聖なる方エホバ」は
the Holy One of Israel,” has bought us back
私たちを買い戻し
from bondage to sin and death
罪と死から自由にしてくださいました
through the ransom sacrifice of Jesus Christ.
イエス・キリストの
贖いの犠牲によってです
それで 不完全な人間も
And thus with faith
イエス・キリストの贖いの犠牲に
信仰を持つなら
in the ransom sacrifice of Jesus Christ,
imperfect people are considered righteous
in the sight of God.
神から正しいと見ていただけます
私たちを正しい人と呼ぶエホバ神は
Now, in calling us righteous,
Jehovah God by means of Jesus
不完全な状態にある
私たち自身にはできないことを
has done something for us
that we could not do
イエスによってしてくださいました
for ourselves in our imperfect condition.
これは私たちが悪いことをすることは
もうないということでしょうか
But does that mean that we can do no wrong?
いいえ そういうことではありません
No, it does not mean that.
平和を保つには
In order to maintain our peace,
we must cooperate with Jehovah.
エホバの言われることを
聞く必要があります
Turn with me, please, to Romans chapter 1.
どうぞローマ 1章をお開きください
ノアやアブラハムと同じく
私たちが生きる世界には
Now, like Noah and Abraham,
we live in a wicked and violent world
悪と暴力 不従順の精神が
広く見られます
where we are exposed
to a spirit of disobedience.
サタンは私たちが
正しくない基準を受け入れて
Satan wants us to become part of this world
by adopting its unrighteous standards.
この世の一部となることを願っています
In the world, sexual immorality
is practiced without shame.
世の中では 性的不道徳が平然と行われ
Homosexuals flaunt their conduct.
同性愛者がもてはやされています
しかしエホバは 同性愛行為は
正しくないと教えています
But Jehovah tells us
that homosexual acts are unrighteous.
God specifically warned the Israelites
エホバ神は こうした
不道徳行為について
against this and other forms of immorality.
イスラエル人に具体的に警告しました
Leviticus 18:22 says
レビ記 18:22には
同性愛行為は「忌まわしい」と
述べられています
that homosexual acts are “detestable.”
エホバは今もそう感じていますか
Does Jehovah still find it so offensive?
Well, notice what he inspired
for both Jews and non-Jews
ユダヤ人とユダヤ人でない人の
両方に宛てて
ギリシャ語聖書の
ローマ 1:26, 27に
in the Christian Greek Scriptures here
at Romans 1:26, 27:
書かれている言葉に注目しましょう
“That is why God gave them over
「それで 神は彼らが
恥ずべき性欲に溺れるままにしました
“to disgraceful sexual passion,
“for their females changed the natural use
女性は自然に反して
女性同士で関係を持ち
“of themselves into one contrary to nature;
“likewise also the males left
the natural use of the female
男性も女性と自然な関係を持つ代わりに
“and became violently inflamed
in their lust toward one another,
男性同士で欲情を激しく燃やし
みだらなことを行って
“males with males, working what is obscene
十分な罰を受けました
“and receiving
in themselves the full penalty,
過ちに対して当然の罰です」
which was due for their error.”
So Jehovah has not changed.
エホバは変わることのない方です
創造者によれば同性愛行為というのは
According to the Creator, homosexual acts
constitute disgraceful,
恥ずべき みだらな行いです
obscene error.
Some would disagree.
そうは考えず 28節にあるように
As verse 28 points out,
「神を認め」る必要などないという
見方をする人もいます
such ones do not consider it
worthwhile “to acknowledge God.”
でも その結果は聖句の通り
But with what result?
As it says there,
“a disapproved mental state”
「堕落した考え方」
平和とは程遠い精神状態です
—just the opposite of peace.
And merely approving
of unrighteous conduct displeases Jehovah.
正しくない行いを認めるだけでも
エホバを不快にさせます
Notice how this is indicated in verse 32:
32節からそれが分かります
“Although these know full well
the righteous decree of God
「彼らは こうした事柄を習慣に
する人は死に値するという
神の正しい規定を
十分に知っているにもかかわらず
“—that those practicing such things
are deserving of death—
そのようなことを行い続けます
“they not only keep on doing them
それだけでなく それを習慣に
している人たちを肯定しています」
but also approve of those practicing them.”
でも私たちは 正しくないことをする人
自身を嫌ったり批判したりはしません
Still, we do not hate individuals
who practice unrighteousness,
nor do we judge them.
そうではなく その人に
良い知らせを伝えます
On the contrary,
we share the good news with them.
We remember that we were all born
with the same infirmities
私たちは皆 生まれながらに同じ
弱さや罪深い傾向を持っています
and have the same sinful tendencies.
同時に皆 神の導きを求める
必要も持っています
But we also have
the same inherent spiritual need.
それでほかの人たちも
エホバに注意を向けるなら
And thus, we recognize that others
can have the same peace,
私たちと同じ平和 誉れ
見込みを持つことができるのです
the same privileges,
and the same prospects we enjoy
if they pay attention to Jehovah.
テモテ第一 2:3, 4にある通り
First Timothy 2:3, 4 says
that God’s “will is that all sorts of people
「神は あらゆる人が救われて
should be saved
and come to an accurate knowledge of truth.”
真理の正確な知識を
得ることを望んでいます」
And people practicing
all manner of unrighteousness
あらゆる正しくない行いをした人たちが
真理を受け入れています
have accepted the truth.
「皆さんの中には 以前そのような人も
いました」とコリントの聖句にあります
“That is what some of you were,”
1 Corinthians 6:11 says.
So we communicate impartially
with all our neighbors.
それで 私たちは全ての人に
分け隔てなく伝道します
But we hate unrighteous conduct,
でも 正しくない行いを憎み
and we refuse to compromise Bible principles.
聖書の原則を曲げたりはしません
Now, sometimes moral issues
道徳的な問題が政治的な議論の
的になることがありますが
become the center
of heated political debates.
私たちはそれに
巻き込まれないようにします
We avoid getting drawn
into such controversies.
But now, in practical terms,
what might that look like?
実際の生活の中で
どんな場面が考えられますか
In the following video, notice how adults
次のビデオで 議論になる問題について
can respond effectively when questioned
on highly controversial issues.
職場でどのように上手に答えることが
できるかに注目してください
There you are.
あ いたいた
Did you both get the email survey I sent?
メール送ったんだけど 見た？
2人とも来れるよね？
And you’re both coming, right?
I must have missed it.
I was on calls all morning.
今朝は忙しくてまだ見れてないです
何のことですか
What’s this about?
Well, the whole office is leaving early.
社員全員が早く上がって
デモに参加するんだ
We’re going downtown
to support the march
同性愛の権利のね
for gay rights.
アイリーンは行かないですよ
She won’t go.
Why?
なんで？
宗教ですよ
It’s against her religion.
彼女のグループの人たちが
うちに来たときに聞いたら
Some of her people came by my house,
and when I asked, they said your church
同性愛者の結婚は支持しないって
言ってました
won’t support gay marriage.
Irene?
そうなの？
It’s true.
はい 結婚は男女間のものと
聖書は教えているので
As Jehovah’s Witnesses,
we hold to the Bible’s standard on marriage,
which is only between a man and woman.
エホバの証人はそれに従っているんです
それに 政治については
中立でいるんです
And we remain politically neutral.
そんな考え古いわよ
That’s such ignorant thinking.
I understand it’s a sensitive subject.
これについては
いろんな意見があるわよね
娘は同性愛者なの
それを主張する権利はあるはずよ
I have a daughter who deserves her rights!
Trust me, Amber,
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
アンバー エホバの証人は
ほかの人がどう生きるかを
決める権利を否定したりはしないわ
we believe everyone has a right
to choose how they live.
And I would never force my beliefs on anyone.
信じていることを
押し付けることもしない
でも行かないんでしょ
But you won’t go.
信じていることを私は押し付けない
Just as I would never force
my beliefs on you,
all I ask is the same respect.
だから私の考えも尊重してほしいの
And, no, I won’t be going.
私は行かない
I have to go back to work.
仕事に戻るわ
Look, obviously, Irene,
まあ 私個人としては
I don’t agree with your perspective.
君の意見には同意しかねるけど
But I do appreciate
that you not push it on anyone else.
君が意見を押し付けたりしないから
助かってるよ
Thank you.
ありがとうございます
In contrast with the majority of mankind
who are divided,
分裂した世界の多くの人々とは異なり
真のクリスチャンは一致しています
true Christians are united.
We loyally support Jehovah’s right to rule.
私たちはエホバの主権を固く支持します
基準を定めたり世界の問題を
自分たちで解決しようとしたりせず
We don’t set the standards,
and we’re not trying
to solve the world’s problems on our own.
神の王国をしっかり支持します
We fully support God’s Kingdom.
Now, as we observed in the video,
ビデオのように 職場で道徳や
政治の問題の話になることがあります
moral and political issues
might be brought up in the workplace.
But more often our young ones,
even very young ones,
さらに 若い人 小さな子でも
そうしたことについて
尋ねられる場合があります
are confronted with these same topics.
How will they respond?
どう答えますか
Are your young ones ready?
準備はできていますか
As you watch the next video,
次のビデオで オリビアが
notice how Olivia defends
Jehovah’s righteous standards.
エホバの正しい基準を
どのように擁護するか見てみましょう
みんな
いいグループディスカッションだった
Great discussion today, everyone.
Remember, midterms are this Friday.
金曜日は中間テストだぞ
No excuses!
ちゃんと勉強しとけ
ジョーダン おまえもな
That includes you, Jordan.
オリビア 今日はあまり
発言してなかったな
You were noticeably silent
during our discussion today, Olivia.
I was?
そうですか？
あまり言うこともなかったので
I guess I just didn’t have much to say.
同性愛者の権利について考えないのか
Aren’t you concerned about gay rights?
Um,
ああ 政治的な問題かなって思うので
well, it seems like a political issue,
and I stay neutral
when it comes to political stuff.
そういうことには
中立でいるようにしているんです
今話しているのは政治の問題じゃない
人権の問題だよ
But it’s not a political issue.
This is a human rights issue.
Mr. Dallas,
先生 オリビアは宗教に
のめり込み過ぎなんですよ
she’s like crazy religious.
いや 宗教自体は悪くないだろ
Hey!
There’s nothing wrong with that.
No, you don’t understand.
違うんですよ エホバの証人は
同性愛者を嫌ってるんです
Jehovah’s Witnesses
hate everybody that isn’t straight.
それは違う！ 嫌ってないよ
That’s not true!
We don’t hate anyone.
I’ve spoken with your people before.
エホバの証人と話したことならある
人を公平に見ている感じがしたよ
They seem big on equality.
We are.
そうなんです 聖書には「神が
不公平ではない」ってあるんです
The Bible says that ‘God isn’t partial.’
So we believe that everyone
should be treated fairly.
だからみんな平等だって
思ってるんですよ
それは良かった
Good.
じゃあ 君の教会には
同性愛の人もいるんだね？
So I assume you have
gay members in your church.
うーん いえ いません
No, we don’t.
But I thought you just said
everyone should be treated equally?
でも今 みんな平等だって言ってたね
なんか矛盾していないか？
I’m confused.
やっぱそうなんだ！
Hah, called it!
ジョーダン
次の授業あるんじゃないのか？
Jordan, don’t you have a class to get to?
さっき言ったけど
As I was saying,
みんなを愛するって言いながら
how is that not a little hypocritical,
特定の人を排除するのは
矛盾していないか？
saying that you love everyone
and then excluding certain people?
正直な話
Honestly, Mr. Dallas,
私もそれ思ったことあるんです
I’ve wondered the same thing.
OK.
おう そうか
で？
And?
で 聖書を調べてみて分かったんです
Well, I researched it in the Bible,
and I realized
神は全ての人を受け入れるけど
that God accepts all people,
but he doesn’t accept all conduct.
全ての行動を
受け入れるわけじゃないって
What does that mean?
どういう意味？
It means that you can’t be abusing drugs
薬物を使ったり 盗みをしたり
and you can’t be stealing
暴力を振るう人が
or be violent and still be a Witness.
エホバの証人に
なることはできないってことです
そういう行いは
神に受け入れられないんです
There are just certain actions
that God just doesn’t accept.
その中に 性に関することも
入っているということか？
Including how someone expresses
their sexuality?
ある意味 そうです
In some cases, yes.
神の考えに従って 結婚していない
人同士のセックスをしないとか
We follow God’s standards
—not having sex without being married.
そうか
Well,
if that’s how you feel, that’s your right.
どう考えるかは
それはそれで君の権利だ
Personally, it seems a tad archaic to me
私としてはちょっと古く聞こえるけど
まあ 人それぞれだから
but to each their own.
ねえ
Hey.
うん
Does the Bible really say all that?
本当に聖書にそういうこと
書いてあるの？
Yeah, it does.
うん そうだよ
OK,
そうなんだ 今度見せてくれる？
maybe you can show me sometime.
うん もちろん
Yeah, for sure.
ありがとう
Awesome.
So we can expect future installments
in this saga.
このビデオには
まだまだ続きがありそうですね
But did you notice how Olivia
オリビアがエホバの正しい基準を
どのように擁護できたか分かりましたか
was able to defend
Jehovah’s righteous standards?
She kept her peaceful spirit, didn’t she?
平和な雰囲気を保ちましたね
先生と同じ疑問を
持ったことがありましたが
She acknowledged that she had
the same question as the teacher,
その点をよく調べていました
but she had done further
research on the subject.
And did you appreciate how she
subtly showed that Jehovah’s standards
オリビアは エホバの基準が個人の
ためにも社会のためにもなることを
benefit both the individual
and the community?
よく説明していたと思いませんか
As examples, she highlighted
the avoidance of drug abuse and theft,
薬物乱用や盗みを避けるといった
先生が同意できると分かっている点を
例に挙げました
values she knew her teacher would appreciate.
親の皆さん お子さんは
Parents, are your young ones
あることをする理由や
しない理由を説明できますか
able to explain why we do
or don’t do certain things?
お子さんがエホバの基準について
正直どう感じているか ご存じですか
Do you know how your children
really feel about Jehovah’s standards?
あなたを怒らせたくない
というだけで従っていますか
Are they obedient simply
to avoid making you mad?
If so, will that truly be enough?
もしそうなら
それで本当にいいでしょうか
Encourage your young ones
エホバの基準がためになる理由を
to prove to themselves
why Jehovah’s standards are wise.
お子さんが確信できるようにしましょう
Help them to see how they can explain
エホバの基準に沿った生き方を選んだ
ことを説明できるように助けてください
their choice to live by Jehovah’s standards.
Teach them how to resist pressure
to follow the world.
周りからの圧力に
どのように抵抗できるか教えましょう
We are so thankful
ありがたいことに
that even during these
“critical times hard to deal with”
この「困難で危機的な時」にも
エホバが与えてくださる心の平和を
得ることができます
we can enjoy the inner peace
that Jehovah gives to the righteous.
But let’s remind ourselves of what Jehovah
promises to bring about
でも エホバがサタンの正しくない体制
を取り除いた後にもたらすと
once Satan’s unrighteous system is removed.
約束しているものについても
考えましょう
Turn with me, please, to Psalm 37.
詩編 37編をお開きください
Here in these familiar verses,
なじみある聖句の中に
we find a beautiful description
of what is to come.
これから起きることが
美しく描かれています
And notice once again
ここでも 聖書が平和と正しさを
how the Bible makes the correlation
どのように結び付けているかに
注目しましょう
between peace and righteousness
詩編 37:29
—Psalm 37:29.
Do you have it?
そこには 何とありますか
What does it say?
誰が地上に住みますか
「正しい人」です
Who will possess the earth?
“The righteous.”
And for how long will they live on it?
どれほどの期間住みますか
“Forever.”
「永遠」です
And then according to verse 11,
what will they find there?
そして11節によれば
そこには何がありますか
「平和」です
“Peace.”
The result of true righteousness
will be peace.
真の正しさは平和をもたらします
どれほどの平和ですか
少しの平和 個人や家族の平和ですか
And how much peace will they find?
a little peace?
just personal or family peace?
でも 正しい人は邪悪な人がいる中でも
神との平和を持っていました
Remember, the righteous
already had peace with God,
even when wicked people still existed.
ではエホバはご自分を愛し続ける人
全てに何を与えてくださいますか
But what will Jehovah provide
to all those who continue loving him?
豊かな平和とあります
The abundance of peace.
And how will you feel about that?
それを聞いてどう感じますか
Delighted or exquisitely delighted?
喜ぶでしょうか
この上なく喜ぶでしょうか
では頑張りましょう
So stick with it, dear friends.
大会の間 平和と正しさのつながりに
注意を払ってください
During this convention, be on the lookout
for the connection
between peace and righteousness.
正しい行いを続け
Continue on the course of righteousness.
ほかの人が「平和の道」を
見つけるのを助けましょう
Help others to find “the way of peace.”
そうするなら エホバとの平和を今
この終わりの時代の間ずっと
In that way, we can enjoy peace
with Jehovah now,
throughout the remainder of these last days,
そして将来も楽しめます
and on into the future when Jesus
rules as King over a cleansed earth
イエスが王として地上を治める時
「正しい人たちは幸せに暮らし
平和が行き渡る」のです
in which “the righteous will flourish
and peace will abound.”
Thank you, Brother Schafer,
for helping us to understand
シェーファー兄弟
ありがとうございました
エホバから見て正しいことを行えば
why upholding Jehovah’s righteousness
本当の平和を味わえる
ということがよく分かりました
is essential for enjoying true peace.
We have been well-instructed
大会初日の午前の部から
本当に多くのことを
学べたのではないでしょうか
during this first session of our convention,
haven’t we?
午後の部も楽しみにしましょう
We look forward to our next session
聖書に書かれている
平和に関する約束について
in which we will consider in greater detail
promises of peace found in God’s Word.
さらに詳しく学ぶことができます
また 家庭をいっそう平和にするために
We will also see how Bible principles
can help families
聖書の教えがどのように役立つかや
to enjoy greater peace now
偽物の平和に惑わされないために
どうすればいいかを考えます
and how we can avoid pursuing
imitation peace.
では 午前の部の最後に
Now let’s conclude this session
97番の賛美の歌を歌いましょう
by singing song number 97, entitled
「神の言葉によって生きる」
という歌です
“Life Depends on God’s Word.”
After singing the song,
歌の後 それぞれの場所で
祈りを捧げてください
you may have your local concluding prayer.
Again, that’s song number 97.
では97番の歌を歌いましょう